What if just one
lifestyle change
could help you
avoid getting cancer,
or diabetes,
or heart disease,
or high blood pressure?
This one change could cut
your risk of chronic disease
and add years to your life.
Well, the simple solution to
so many of these problems
is to eat a healthy diet.
In other words, one centered
around whole plant foods.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I'm your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we look a problem that many
men experience from time to time,
erectile dysfunction.
And we start by looking
at the nuts.
I’m talking about walnuts,
almonds and hazelnuts.
Here’s the story.
In 2013 — I can't believe it's already
been so long — I posted a video
based on this study, that found that
three weeks of pistachios resulted
in a significant improvement
in erectile function in men.
It's always nice to see a whole food
intervention have clinical effects,
and I was curious to revisit the topic
to see what's been published since.
Even if you ignore all the lab
animal studies on, you know,
how much hazelnuts improve
the function of rat testicles,
you still never know what you'll find
searching the medical literature
for nuts and sexual function,
like this case of penile
strangulation with a metal hex nut.
I guess nuts can sometimes make
things worse if you can't remove them.
They used the Dundee technique, which
involves creating 20 puncture holes
to relieve the pressure,
but that didn't work.
So a diamond disk cutter
was used to saw through it,
and they slipped a few times.
All's well that ends well.
Well, that got me curious.
Evidently, penile entrapment
is so common,
there's an entire grading system
that emergency room docs can use.
If a drill is not available,
these surgeons advise
a hammer and chisel may be used.
A drill? Oh, a dental drill.
I like how they brag about
the precisely cut edges.
Looks pretty jagged to me.
To "preserve the penis
from a fatal outcome"
(that's a strange way to put it),
urologists should be aware of all
the available armamentarium,
and if you don't know how
to operate the saw,
you can always call in
your local blacksmith.
Yet, how are you going to remove a
barbell or steel sledgehammer head?
A heavy-duty air grinder provided by
the fire department, requiring 6 hours
of cutting, with the patient protected
from the sparks with fire coats
whatever it takes.
Hack saw. Cement eater.
Or the silk winding method.
But anyway, back
to the task at hand.
Consumption of at least one serving
of vegetables a day and more than
two servings of nuts a week
was associated with more than
a 50% decrease in the probability
of erectile dysfunction
in a snapshot-in-time
cross-sectional study.
But such observational studies
can't prove cause-and-effect.
It's like finding that men who eat more
healthfully have better swimmers.
Maybe men who eat nuts
are just health nuts,
and the improvement is due to
some other factor like exercise.
What we need is an interventional
trial, and here we go.
The effect of nut consumption on
semen quality and functionality:
a randomized controlled trial.
A Standard American Diet, with
or without a handful of walnuts,
and a half handful of each
almonds and hazelnuts.
And the nut group experienced
significant improvements
in their total sperm count,
vitality, motility, and shape,
perhaps because those
in the nut group
showed a significant reduction
in SDF: sperm DNA fragmentation.
The nuts appeared to
protect their sperm DNA.
Too bad while they were at it,
they didn't measure the guys'
erectile and sexual dysfunction.
Oh, but they did!
The effect of nut consumption on erectile
and sexual function from the same study.
The researchers report that those in
the nut group saw a significant increase
in orgasmic function and sexual desire,
but what about erectile function?
Any time you see this kind of
selective glass-half-full reporting
you suspect some kind
of industry funding,
and indeed that was the case here.
Yes, there was a marginal increase in
orgasmic function and sexual desire
of questionable clinical significance,
but no improvement in erectile function,
intercourse satisfaction,
or overall satisfaction.
And with so many comparisons,
even the so-called significant findings
may not even be
statistically significant.
But why did the pistachios
I talked about back in 2013 work,
while these other nuts didn't?
Well, if you remember, the
original study was done on men
in their 40s and 50s who already
had chronic erectile dysfunction,
whereas the average age in
the new study was 24 years old.
So they may have started out
with near-maximum circulation,
not leaving much
room for the nuts.
In our next story, we look at
how men eating pistachio nuts
experienced a significant
improvement in blood flow
through the penis accompanied
by significantly firmer erections.
Here’s the story.
Erectile dysfunction is
considered an important cause
of decreased quality
of life in men,
in fact, so much so that
one early theory suggested
that this may
explain the link
between impotence
and heart attacks.
Depression is a risk factor
for coronary heart disease,
and the thought was that
men who couldn't get it up
become so depressed that they
like "die" of a broken heart.
But now we know that erectile
dysfunction and heart disease
can be two different
manifestations
of the exact same
root problem,
DISEASED ARTERIES—
inflamed, oxidized, cholesterol-clogged
blood vessels.
So, no wonder a diet chock
full of anti-inflammatory,
antioxidant, cholesterol-
lowering plant foods
would improve sexual functioning
in both men and women
as well as reduce risk
of heart disease.
But why go LOW risk when
you can shoot for NO risk?
A totally
plant-based diet
can even stop and reverse
our number one killer.
Of all the plant foods
individually examined so far,
nuts are among those
most tied to longevity.
Just two handfuls a week
may extend a woman's life
as much as jogging
4 hours a week.
So, if nuts reduce
the risk of heart disease,
might they also help
with sexual function?
Well, men eating 3 to 4 handfuls
of pistachios a day
for just 3 weeks experienced
a significant improvement
in blood flow
through the penis
accompanied by significantly
firmer erections.
This may not
be surprising.
Remember how antioxidant-rich foods
have a Viagra-like effect
of boosting nitric oxide production?
Well, pistachios are certainly
rich sources of antioxidants.
And remember how the
citruline in watermelons
helped with erection firmness
by boosting arginine,
which is what our body makes
nitric oxide out of?
Well, pistachios have
a bunch of arginine,
which may help explain the
improvement in blood flow.
And we know that cholesterol
is an important predictor
of sexual dysfunction
in both men and women,
and after just 3 weeks
on all those pistachios
there were significant
improvements in cholesterol.
And like other studies
that piled on
hundreds of calories of nuts
a day there was no weight gain.
Conclusion: just 3 weeks
of pistachios
resulted in a significant
improvement in erectile function
with additional improvement
in cholesterol
without any side effects.
Note the 2 important differences
between diet and drugs.
Just taking drugs like Viagra
to poison this enzyme
and artificially boost
nitric oxide signaling
is just covering
up the symptoms
of the underlying problem:
UNHEALTHY ARTERIES.
Whereas eating whole healthy
plant foods like nuts
actually helps attack
the root cause—
cholesterol, oxidation,
and inflammation—
and only has good
side effects.
This enzyme that Viagra-like
drugs muck with
is primarily found in
2 places in the body:
the erectile tissue of the penis
and the retina of the eye.
That's why the FDA
encourages people
to stop taking
drugs like viagra,
and call a doctor right away
if you experience sudden
loss of vision,
if of course you can
still find your phone.
Though the harms tend to be
self-limited and reversible,
such as cyanopsia in
which your vision
suddenly becomes tinted blue.
Why risk side-effects at all,
when the problem can be reversed,
cured in the first place,
improving the quality and
quantity of our lives?
"Improvement of sexual
function in men (and women)"
"should be added to the growing
list of clinical benefits"
"brought about by healthy
lifestyles in human beings."
Did you know that dioxins,
endocrine disrupting pollutants,
heavy metals, saturated fat,
and steroids in the meat supply
may be affecting sperm counts,
semen quality,
and the ability of
men to conceive?
Infertility affects 10--15%
of couples attempting to conceive
and in about half the cases
the problem is found in the man.
A recent Harvard study found that
increasing saturated fat intake just 5%
was associated with a 38%
lower sperm count. But why?
I've talked about the role of xenoestrogens,
endocrine disrupting industrial pollutants
that build up in animal fat,
particularly fish,
but male fertility is not just
about sperm count—the number of sperm,
but about how well
the sperms themselves work.
A recent study found that "successful pregnancy
and fertilized egg implantation outcomes"
"are decreased in patients reporting
a more frequent intake of meat."
"This finding is consistent
with poor semen quality
associated with a higher intake of products"
that may incorporate these
chemicals and steroids.
"The use of these compounds in the food industry
results in an increased
total level of xenoestrogens"
"and sex steroids in processed foods,
such as meat or milk,
whose intake contributes
significantly to daily exposures".
"Xenoestrogens are
highly lipophilic substances
that can accumulate in
fat-rich foods, such as meat,"
"and may be suspected as partially
responsible for the decline in semen quality."
"Conclusion: Couples having trouble
conceiving must be advised"
"about the drastic effect of both the male
and female lifestyle on treatment success."
This is consistent with previous
findings that frequent intake
of fat-laden foods like,
meat products and milk
"may negatively affect
semen quality in humans,"
"whereas some fruits or vegetables
may maintain or improve semen quality."
Vegetable consumption was also
found protective in the new study,
which may be because of the antioxidant
and nutrient content of these plant foods.
The adverse effects of meat
could be from other pollutants as well.
Exposure even as an infant
to low levels of dioxin
can permanently
reduce sperm quality.
The general consensus is that human sperm quality
has declined over time in different areas.
We're still not sure why,
but dioxins may be playing a causal role.
The reason why maternal beef consumption
may alter a man's testicular development
and adversely affect his future
reproductive capacity
is thought to be due to the anabolic
steroids implanted into the animals,
but as the accompanying
editorial points out,
the steroids could also be
interacting with other xenobiotic,
meaning industrial chemicals present in meat,
such as pesticides and dioxin-like pollutants,
and even chemicals that may be
present in the plastic wrap.
Heavy metals may
also play a role.
Lead and cadmium exposure
as measured in the bloodstream
was associated with significantly
longer time to conceive.
Where might exposure
be coming from?
Common types of seafood right out of
fish markets and supermarkets were sampled.
The highest cadmium levels were found in tuna;
highest lead levels were
found in scallops and shrimp.
The greatest risk from different metals resided in
different fish; some of which got really high.
"Thus, the risk information given
to the public (mainly about mercury)
does not present
a complete picture."
There are other toxic metals
in fish as well.
The largest and oldest fish
had some of the highest levels,
and we see that with other
animals as well,
for example, contamination
of beef by cadmium and lead,
clearly dependent on
the age of the animal.
The only beverage associated with
infertility in women was soft drinks,
though this may be from an indirect route,
with soda linked to obesity
and then obesity then linked to
reduced fertilization rates,
though there has been a study
on one really direct route,
the effectiveness of Coca Cola as a
spermicidal agent in vaginal douching.
Diet coke apparently
had the strongest effect.
Harvard researchers publishing
in the New England Journal of Medicine.
What about Coke versus Pepsi?
Tax-payer money hard at
work for this head to head test.
And neither of them really worked -
Coke nor Pepsi,
though they explain their methods for
preparing the sperm-Cola mixtures
differed from the
Harvard group.
Bottomline: soda probably isn't good
for you going into any orifice.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts Podcast
landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite to each of these topics.
My latest two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”,
available on e-book, audiobook,
or actual book.
And the “How Not to Diet Cookbook”,
with more than 100 recipes for
delicious and nutritious meals.
All the proceeds I receive from
the sales of my books go to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the website is free.
There’s no ads, no corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.